[PREVIEW] DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly: #mainContent { float: none; padding-top: 2em; padding-left: 4em; padding-right: 4em; margin-left: 225px; } [PREVIEW] DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly: #mainContent { float: none; padding-top: 2em; padding-left: 4em; padding-right: 4em; margin-left: 225px; } [PREVIEW] DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly: #mainContent { float: none; padding-top: 2em; padding-left: 4em; padding-right: 4em; margin-left: 225px; } [PREVIEW] DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly: #mainContent { float: none; padding-top: 2em; padding-left: 4em; padding-right: 4em; margin-left: 225px; } Preview Preview  |  XML |  Print Article 2025-04-30 Adapting a Research Tool for Teaching in a Post-Pandemic World: Textual Communities and Critical Digital Pedagogy in the Context of a Comprehensive Liberal Arts Research University Textual Communities and Critical Digital Pedagogy in the Context of a Comprehensive Liberal Arts Research University Blurb for social media 1 How can digital tools originally developed for research reshape undergraduate teaching? The authors adapt the Textual Communities research-tool for using it in a paleography class, and reflect on critical digital pedagogy, hybrid learning environments, and the transformative potential of scholarly infrastructure in the classroom. Bios Barbara Bordalejo, University of Lethbridge, barbara.bordalejo@uleth.ca, https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8255-0265 2 Barbara Bordalejo is a textual scholar, editor, and digital humanist whose work spans digital editing, manuscript studies, and the politics of knowledge production in the humanities. She holds PhDs from New York University and De Montfort University, and she is Director of the Canterbury Tales Project and Publishing Director at Scholarly Digital Editions. Currently an Adjunct Professor at the University of Lethbridge, she has previously held academic appointments in Canada, the UK, Belgium, and Italy. Her research interests include AI and data ethics in higher education, the application of bioinformatics to textual criticism, and intersectional feminist approaches to scholarly editing. Barbara serves as President of the Canadian Society for Digital Humanities and sits on the editorial board of Digital Scholarship in the Humanities. Her recent publications explore AI-assisted writing, digital pedagogy, and critical approaches to the unessay. Davide Pafumi, University of Lethbridge, davide.pafumi@uleth.ca, https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1113-187X 3 Davide Pafumi is a doctoral candidate at the University of Lethbridge specializing in medieval studies and Digital Humanities. His research focuses on medieval literature, historical linguistics, paleography, and computational approaches to address complex Humanities research questions. He serves as a research assistant to the “Canterbury Tales Project,” where he works on the transcription, editing, and encoding of the 88 pre-modern manuscripts in Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales textual tradition. Davide has received several prestigious awards in the field of medieval studies, including the 2023 Benton-Mahoney Award from the Medieval Association of the Pacific and the 2025 Founders Grant from the International Courtly Literature Society (North American Branch). In 2021, he graduated with Honours from the University of Padua, earning MA in English and German Linguistics and Literatures. Morgan S. Pearce, University of Lethbridge, morgan.pearce@uleth.ca, https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1768-4501 4 Morgan Slayde Pearce is a master’s student at the University of Lethbridge and a member of the Humanities Innovation Lab. She is a research assistant for the Lethbridge Journal Incubator and the “Canterbury Tales Project.” Her thesis combines medieval literary studies and game studies to look at how non-linear narratives in various genres and media are used to convey the experience of depression and loss, specifically through the use of the symbol of the labyrinth. Her research combines studies of the history of the book, medieval literature, game studies, and digital humanities. Morgan received the Alberta Graduate Excellence Scholarship in 2023 and the Benton-Mahoney Award from the Medieval Association of the Pacific in 2024. She graduated from the University of Lethbridge with her BA in English in 2021 with Great Distinction. Daniel Paul O’Donnell, University of Lethbridge, daniel.odonnell@uleth.ca, https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0127-4893 5 Daniel Paul O’Donnell is a Professor of English and Department Chair at the University of Lethbridge. His research and teaching focuses on Digital Humanities, the formation and practice of the humanities, Open Science, and early medieval philology and textual criticism. He is the author of Cædmon’s Hymn, A Multimedia Archive, Edition, and Study (Medieval Academy of America/SEENET, 2005, and a co-author of Reading Peer Review: PLOS ONE and Institutional Change in Academia (Cambridge University Press, 2020). During the pandemic, he was PI on a Sloan-funded project examining how Open Science instruction was adapting to an online environment. Abstract 6 This article examines the pedagogical adaptation of Textual Communities, a digital tool originally developed for collaborative research in textual scholarship, to teach paleography at the undergraduate level within a liberal arts context. Prompted by the exigencies of remote learning during the COVID-19 pandemic and the broader framework of critical digital pedagogy, the course-design reimagined the tool’s primary research-focused function — edition-making— as a dynamic teaching and learning environment emphasizing transcription, engagement, and student autonomy. The article presents a specific example of the use of a digital tool in teaching paleography, detailing its purpose and impact on student learning and engagement. The article offers a concrete case study of hybrid- and flexible-by-design pedagogy, showing the value of using scholarly digital tools in undergraduate settings. 7 Keywords: pedagogy, tools, transcription, manuscripts, infrastructure. Introduction 8 The changes experienced by teachers and studentsthe higher education community following the outbreak of COVID-19 remain unprecedented in light of its impact on different spheres of collective life. Paraphrasing Marcel Mauss, the pandemic stoodcan be viewed as a “total social fact” (Mauss, 1966, pp. 76–77),(Mauss, 1966, pp. 76–77), playing a pivotal role in social change in light ofdue to its significant “implications throughout society” (Edgar and Sedgwick, 1999, p. 64)(Edgar and Sedgwick, 1999, p. 64). Against this backdrop, this paper addresses the spheres of teaching digital humanities, specifically in the aftermath of the pandemic. 9 In 2023, the departments of English and History at the University of Lethbridge approved an undergraduate advanced course, bothunder the leadership of Barbara Bordalejo, for English and History students, on paleography of the British Isles covering texts in Latin, Old French, Old and Middle English produced between 800 and 1500 under the leadership of Barbara Bordalejo.. When designing the course, we decided to implementthe authors of this paper implemented Textual Communities, (Bordalejo and Robinson, 2016), a collaborative online research system wherethat allows participants canto work asynchronously, which we adapted for pedagogical purposes. Because of Bordalejo’s experience during the Fall of 2021, when a surge of the COVID Delta variant forced all academic staff to pivot to online teaching, Textual Communities was as much about its pedagogical promise as its potential use as a distance learning tool. In this paper, we have drawndraw from aour practical experience of a course of this kind towith the platform and extrapolate a systematic discussion of itsthe implications of the adaptation and use of a research tool for pedagogical purposes. One of these implications is undoubtedly how the lockdown forced academics and teachers to repurpose existing tools developed for different purposesends, such as Textual Communities, with the aim of easily switching from in-person to remote if and when required. The students would have the opportunity to work from home or anywhere else while continuing to receive constant feedback on their work from the instructors. But another in the implications of allowing students access to research tools — and allowing them some of the flexibility we enjoy as researchers ourselves — as a form of critical pedagogy. 10 In the wake of COVID, a considerable amount of related literature has emerged on implementing digital technology in higher educational contexts (Akbar, 2016; Lai, 2011), focusing on two main aspects of remote teaching and learning. The extensive body of literature on this matter has centeredAkbar, 2016; Lai, 2011). These studies centred around the consequences of the pandemic on teaching and learning at different levels, highlighting the drawbacks and opportunities of remote teaching and learning in this context (Murphy, 2020; Hofer et al., 2021) and at the same time theorizing(e.g. Murphy, 2020; Hofer, Nistor, and Scheibenzuber, 2021); they also theorized ways in which to normalize e-Learning Pedagogies for the near future (Barrett-Fox et al. 2020; Badilla Quintana et al., 2021). However, scholarship in this field has limited itself to merely theorizing the long-term impact of the lockdown experience without proposing a third alternative: a concrete example of what a successful (post-pandemic course should look like) future (Barrett-Fox et al. 2020; Careaga-Butter et al., 2020). In this paper, we propose a third topic: looking at the implications these techniques and what implementations, if any, should be in place in case of need. 11 tools have for our understanding of what we ask our students to do. This study presents our experiences adapting a research tool (Textual Communities) as to become a pedagogical aid in teachingthe paleography classroom. Our work isserves as a practical instanceexample of dealing withaddressing the aftermath of the pandemic. It provides us with both a sound teaching environment and an effective way to transition to online teaching quickly, should the circumstances require it. By using tools in this flexible manner, we ensure that our students are safeguarded ifshould extreme circumstances arise, whether personal or pertain toaffecting the wholeentire community. We share this experience as a generalizable example and a reproducible strategy for teaching paleography and the history of handwriting. 12 Moreover, the current work presents different perspectives (those of the instructors’instructors, the teaching assistant’sassistants, and the students’students) and experiences to assess the importance of this course, considering its significance afterin the post-COVID-19 era. The paper presents an overview of the existing scholarship on emergency e-learning, provided along with the most recent developments of the discourse surrounding digital pedagogy and specifically its particular inflection, i.e., critical digital pedagogy (Kim, 2018; Stommel, Friend, and Morris, 2020a), whose principles have served as a methodology for this work. TeachingMethods of teaching paleography without computers 13 InPaleography is the study of historical handwriting, traditionally focused on the medieval period. At institutions with strong material resources, includingsuch as a Rare Books Libraryrare books library with manuscript collections, paleographythis class can be taught in conjunction with other aspects of manuscript culture. In such cases, studentsStudents might be asked to identify scripts or read directly from manuscript materials under the direction of a professor or teaching assistant. Even in those cases, lectures are routinely delivered as part of the courses. Tests might include reading or copying from original manuscript materials. The widthbreadth of the subjectcourse is attached, to thea degree in such cases, determined by available materials. A few privileged institutions have wide-rangingInstitutions with extensive collections of manuscripts or that are close enough tolocated near repositories with various materials to make it possible to have alarge holdings can introduce students to a wide range of scripts, languages, and texts covering the desired periods, and codicological forms. 14 Newer institutions and institutions with more limited funding might need access to or holdings can offer a simulacrum of such a course using the increasingly large number of high-quality facsimiles for teaching. In such cases, instructors might rely on digital facsimiles or digital images made freely available online by the repositories holding the manuscripts.from manuscript libraries and other cultural institutions. Access to freely available digital images allows forenables a pedagogical model in which the students read from thosethese images during class, while the instructor clarifies particularparticularly challenging sections. This approach would reflect a triedreflects a practice that has served many generations of paleographers well. The disadvantage of this practice is that it requiresWhether a university has access to the original artifacts or facsimiles, however, smaller classes with very few students in order for all of them to have the opportunity to practice and receivetraditionally been a sine qua non of successful instruction. While lectures are common in such courses, a very important part remains hands-on work with the artifacts or facsimiles themselves, including plenty of one-on-one feedback. Moreover, this practice puts students under pressure to perform in front of their peers. from the instructor. 15 Our pedagogical practice, adapted for a class of 27 students,Our approach we switched the focus from reading aloud to reading and recording. We asked the students to transcribe the manuscript pages in class and on their own time and to include a very light encoding so the transcription could, in theory, be processed by computers. 16 The class’sThis encoding component is an innovation in reference to more traditional approaches to paleography. It allowsThis approach enables students to understandengage with texts as dynamic semiotic systems and , recognizing transcription not as a mere substitution but as an act of translation —from the semiotic system of the manuscript to thethat of the digital transcription (Robinson and Solopova, 1993). As Robinson and Solopova (1993) emphasize, transcriptions are inherently interpretative and incomplete, akin to all translational acts, as they navigate between distinct semiotic system of the transcription.frameworks (e.g., the primary source and the digital medium). Moreover, in the context of the semiotic shift, the students often begininitiate their own reflexive process as to whatregarding why and how texts should be interpreted and transcribed. Institutional context 17 In 2023, Barbara Bordalejo had a class on paleography of the British Isles approved in the departments of English and History at the University of Lethbridge with manuscript selections covering texts in Latin, Old English,French, Old and Middle English produced between 700 and 1500. Although her paleographic training in the late 90s1990s included some access to digital photography (which was of very low quality at the time), she primarily worked with analog materials (, including printed photographs, photocopies, and a few manuscripts).. However, after joining the Canterbury Tales Project, Bordalejo shifted her paleography work to the computer environments, where she worked with digital images taken from old microfilm and transcribed texts encoded in SGML using a custom font called “Canterbury.” The new course's design builds on and integrates these text encoding skills, which are useful for text processing using computers, and commonly implemented in digital humanities. 18 The University of Lethbridge is a comprehensive academic research university (CARU) with a liberal arts institutionfocus that serves a primarily serving undergraduate studentsstudent body. As such, unlike major research larger institutions, the university libraryUniversity of Lethbridge has a limited collection of original materials that might be used for teaching a general paleography class. Historically, the English Department was well-staffed, but budgeting constraints weakened the widthbreadth of the program., reducing its faculty complement by as much as 50%. Bordalejo arrived in the Fall of 2021 to teach medieval literature, digital humanities, and humanities data courses. She proposed three courses that were approved as new offerings: Digital Textuality (English), Humanities Data (Interdisciplinary), and Paleography (English and History). Paleography is offered as a third-year course in both English and History. There arewere no exclusionary prerequisites, but knowledge of Old or Middle English or History of the Book is advantageouswas recommended for those taking the class. The official course syllabus lists(see Bordalejo, 2024) listed the following objectives: 19 1. identify different scripts, 20 2. use correct terminology while referring to different scripts, 21 3. understand the historical context of the studied works, 22 4. read and transcribe scripts of the British Isles, 23 5. formulate research questions regarding paleographic studies. 24 Most students havehad already taken a course focused on medieval history or medieval literature. About half of the class had training in either Old English, Middle English, or the history of the English language. However, there were also students without any knowledge of the subjects listed above.these or similar subjects, including a few from the natural sciences who had very little background in the humanities at all. A common characteristic the vast majority of the students shared was their lack of familiarity with aspects of technology such as encoding. Although we are unable to document this, the sense among the more experienced members of our team is that, at the turn of the century, it was more common for individuals to have at least some knowledge of HTML acquired through practices such as blogging and developing websites in the days before WYSIWYG (What You See Is What You Get) web applications and the rise of social media. While there has been an increase in the access of technology in students’ day-to-day lives this does not necessarily mean there has been a corresponding increase in their understanding of what goes on on the back-end: 25 While many young people use technology daily, this does not necessarily mean that they possess high-order technical skills that will allow them to excel beyond their superficial use of tech gadgets. (Thomas and Blackwood, 2010, p. 8) 26 In fact, while programming languages, such as HTML, remain popular among users — as illustrated in a recent survey by Stack Overflow (2024) — this does not represent a general literacy, as we discovered when we asked students to practice making a small webpage to help them understand on a base level how information must be structured in order to allow the machine to process it. Amongst both offerings of the course we found that students struggled to grasp the fundamental logic of computer languages even before attempting to encode the manuscripts. Literature review 27 The emergence of academic literature on the pandemic’s effectimpact on pedagogy has resulted inled to two contradictory attitudes. One approach focuses more on the short-term implications and views classroom adjustments as a temporary response to the pandemic. At the same time, theThe other is geared towards predicting the potential long-term impact on pedagogy by continuing to implement the new strategies developed during the pandemic. Specifically, onOn the one hand, the first attitude highlights the “risks” associated with an increased dependency and deployment of digital tools and online learning in an educational setting; on the other hand, the second attitude suggests that teaching practices should be informed by the COVID experience to enhance them in the future rather than discarding them once the pandemic is “over.” 28 Murphy’s work is situated within the first approach. They focusMurphy focuses on the consequences of what they defineis defined as “emergency eLearning” (Murphy, 2020, p. 1)(2020, p. 1), criticizing the fact that the pandemic has led to a general “securitization” of higher education’s rising reliance on surveillance technologies and the adoption of one-size-fits-all solutions. They also emphasize the “danger of normalizing emergency eLearning” without falling into the rhetoric of “condemning all forms of online learning”, but still argue for an “emancipation” from the securitization associated with eLearning (Murphy, 2020, p.(Murphy, 2020, p. 10). In this sense, Murphy is one of the most critical voices in the scholarly discussion on the pandemic turn. Still, they focus mainly on the risks — neglecting to address other issues, such as the degree to which technology is helpful in post-pandemic pedagogies and the circumstances from which these changes have come to be. 29 Hofer, Nistor, and Scheibenzuber have discussed the need to re-examine the pandemic experience in terms of its benefits to teaching practices. Consistent with the second stance discussed previously — looking at the lessons learned from the pandemic as a positive — they engage with the emergency aspects taken for granted by Murphy (Hofer et al., 2021).(Hofer et al., 2021). In their contribution, the authors startbegin with the idea that normally transformative processes may not develop in a gradual, cumulative way likemanner, such as the implementation of digital tools in teaching (HoferHofer et al., 2021, p. 2). They argue that changes “can be suddenly triggered by unexpected and compelling incidents or accidents that make up crisis situations,” such as in the case of the pandemic (Hofer et al.Hofer et al. 2021, p. 2). According to their view, this happens mainly because “[c]risis situations emphasize the strengths, uncover the weaknesses, and lead to progress” (Hofer, Nistor, and Scheibenzuber 2021, p.Hofer et al. 2021, p. 2). 30 In the same vein, Barrett-Fox et al. (Barrett-Fox et al. 2020)In the same vein, Barrett-Fox et al. (Barrett-Fox et al., 2020) positively assess this “shift for teaching” in terms of the acceleration of “the use of digital technology”,” whose potential may be regarded as important “for online learning to bring about new pedagogical approaches” (Barrett-Fox et al., 2020Barrett-Fox et al., 2020, p. 154) in the post-pandemic. Barrett-Fox et al. stressemphasize the importance of movingtransitioning from a “restoration” to an all-embracingencompassing “transformation” of teaching practices. This awareness of new approaches and methods to engaging students comes from the realization that during the lockdown, “it became painfully obvious that we could not just do the same thing. Some assignments were no longer possible. Some expectations were no longer reasonable. Some objectives were no longer valuable” (Barrett-Fox et al., 2020Barrett-Fox et al., 2020, pp. 161–162). Thus, they not only discuss the potential benefits of online learning to foster new pedagogical approaches (Barrett-Fox et al., 2020, pp. 183–184),Barrett-Fox et al., 2020, pp. 183–184) but also how such a shift allows increased access to educational resources and opportunities for students to engage in deeper learning. At the same time, they highlight potential drawbacks, such as the potential forrisk that digital technology tomay exacerbate existing inequalities and the need for teachers to acquire new digital skills (Barrett-Fox et al., 2020Barrett-Fox et al., 2020, pp. 185–186). Their contribution joins those who call for further research into the implications of the pandemic and foresee a positive outcome from the wider adoption of online learning and new pedagogies connected to it. 31 Moving away from these two earlier defined attitudes,For their part, Lohr et al. carried out qualitative research was carried out to “address the lack of systematic research on digitally supported learning activities and the institutional and personal factors associated with their occurrence in higher education” (Lohr et al., 2021, p. 2). The(2021, p. 2). Their broader aim was to assess the degree of familiarity of teachers with technology in higher educational environments, and this allowed the identification of three distinct teacher roles: “powerpointers,” “clickers,” and “digital pros” — each of which was shown to be more or less comfortable in the use of digital technologies for teaching purposes. This differentiation also suggests that implementation is not a one-to-one relation and does not necessarily lead to digital pedagogy, even when there is space for digital pedagogical innovation. 32 This idea is not new and has been analyzed by Badilla Quintana, Careaga-Butter, and Fuentes-Henríquez (Badilla Quintana et al., 2021), whoCareaga-Butter et al. (2020) considered thatthe degree to which digital tools and resources that beneficially contributed to online education during the pandemic can continue in the post-pandemic future as well. This is possible only if teachers are willing to adopt and integrate them into their teaching practicepractices and are prepared to offer students the guidance and support necessary to ensure that they can succeedtheir success in their studies. Together with the need “to collaborate in the construction of [...] a new mixed educational paradigm that can face the post-pandemic context and meet the new demands and requirements of the 21st century,” a good-faith effort to integrate digital technologies into the classroom is the only way to achieve a “true online education” in the terms defined by Badilla Quintana, Careaga-Butter, and Fuentes-Henríquez (Badilla Quintana et al., 2021, p.they define (Careaga-Butter et al., 2020, p. 29). 33 COVID-19 was not the sole prompt for using digital tools to teach and learn. For instance, Torsello, Ackerley, and Castello (Torsello et al., 2008Torsello, Ackerley, and Castello (Torsello et al., 2008) and Forti (Forti, 2023)Forti (Forti, 2023) have already proved the usefulness of integrating corpus management programs designed for linguistic analysis into teaching linguistics and translation. Social media platforms such as X (formerly known as Twitter) have also proven to be beneficial both for teaching and learning purposes (Gleason and Manca, 2020; Rinaldo et al., 2011).(Gleason and Manca, 2020; Rinaldo et al., 2011). Notably, the cases mentioned above are the only few examples we found where advanced tools not primarily intended for pedagogical purposes have been repurposed for educational use. Addressing this gap presents an opportunity to expand the array of available resources for educators, potentially enhancing the quality of the teaching and learning process. We addressed this gap through; in our case, it involved the unconventional implementation of Textual Communities in the university classroom environment. What is Textual Communities? 34 Textual Communities is an online application designed for the needs of textual scholars working with texts, mainly found in manuscripts, in multiple versions. It was first established as a project at the University of Saskatchewan with funding from the Canadian Foundation for Innovation (CFI) and support from the U of S’s Digital Research Centre. Its purpose, as described by Robinson, Nelson, and Klaassen is to “provide the infrastructure and tools to allow anyone, anywhere interested in a text to contribute to its study, and thus to become part of a community working together” (2012). As such, it integrates tools for the transcription, collation, regularization, and publication of scholarly editions. Because using a social-network-like model. Since Textual Communities is available online, the system has been ideal for large collaborative projects where participants work asynchronously and might not be physically close. Textual Communities(potentially) at a physical distance. It has a component that provides version control by recording the source, time, and responsibility for changes. Unlike — although, unlike Google Docs, Textual Communities is not optimized to allow real-time simultaneous editing of a single document. (making it more similar to GitHub). Instead, the system keeps track of different versions of transcriptions and records times, duration, and responsibility. In addition, the data created within the communities is made available for “unrestricted commercial as well as non-commercial use” (Robinson, Nelson, and Klaassen, 2012). 35 What sets Textual Communities apart are two features: its integrated participant- and document-management systems, and its mapping of the fundamental structure connecting documents and texts. These reflect two core principles: that assembling large corpora is best achieved through well-managed communities of contributors, both academic and non-academic; and that the usefulness of the corpus depends on clearly articulating the relationships between materials. Textual Communities is designed to organize multiple participants around shared editorial projects. It supports relational structures ranging from tightly controlled editorial teams to loosely organized crowdsourced communities — making it ideal for both classroom use and long-term research. The name “Textual Communities” therefore highlights the importance of community aspects in textual editing and scholarship, which is one reason why the system is easily adaptable for classroom environments. Since the system’s inception in the 2010s, various projects have welcomed collaborators from around the globe. For long-term enterprises like the Canterbury Tales Project, more than one hundred and twenty participants have joined Textual Communities since the implementation of its latest version in 2014. These collaborators are mostly transcribers who have been trained in TEI-XML as well as in paleography and Middle English. The system has been tested, and up to forty participants have been logged into a single project simultaneously, but there is no reason to believe that higher numbers would not work either. How did we adapt Textual Communities to the classroom? 36 Although the goal of a paleography course, traditionally and primarily, has been to train students in the interpretation of hand-written documents, there has always been an element of research apprenticeship involved. Medieval and literary manuscripts are not objects most individuals encounter outside of a research context (i.e., by requesting access for research purposes from academic libraries, museums, and private collectors), and the conventions used to track student observations — such as the Leiden transcription conventions — are those used by researchers (e.g. Wilcken, 1932). 37 Today, digital transcription is the standard for projects interested in text comparison and analysis, whether their outputs are released in print or digitally. Although the study of paleography requires reading handwritten materials and identifying scripts and scribes, paleographers increasingly find themselves working within digital environments that need their own subset of specialized knowledge. Our In adapting Textual Communities to the paleography course, therefore, requiresclassroom, we continue this tradition. At the same time, the more complex needs of a very light introduction to digital environment — which require coding consistency and controlled markup — necessitated that we also teach our students some basic information about computer markup and encoding systems, with particular emphasis on TEI-XML as the standard used for digital projects. These classes were led by Daniel Paul O’Donnell, a former Chair of the TEI consortium. Beyond this basic computational instruction, a series of additional decisions were required in order to implement Textual Communities — which was not designed as a pedagogical tool — into the classroom. How did we adapt Textual Communities to the classroom? 38 Because Textual Communities was not designed with pedagogical goals in mind, a series of decisions were required to use it successfully in the classroom. For this particular class, for example, the transcriptions did not need to be further processed or published, and their long-term availability was not required. For these reasons, wepreservation was not required (indeed privacy regulations at the University require records of student work to be destroyed at set deadlines after the end of a class unless additional permissions have been granted). We thought, therefore, that Textual Communities Sandbox offered an appropriate environment for the students’ work (indeed, this is the version we recommend for anyone testing the software or working on short-term mini-projects). The Textual Communities SandboxThis has most of the same functionalities as the production version. It offers: there are no limitations inon creating communities by any interested parties, but it does not provide archiving and publication facilities. Although it would have been possible to use the production version with the same effect, we chose to create the course within the experimental space. After all, the primary purpose of its use was beyond the regular implementations of Textual Communities, but still required a centralized system that would keep track of work being done and completed by students, as well as keeping track of the hours worked and every change implemented in the texts. Because of its versioning capabilities, Textual Communities allowed us to track in real-time the work being done by the students either in the classroom or outside of it. , either in the classroom or outside of it. As of March 2025, the sandbox environment referenced in this study has been retired. All functionality described in this article is now available through the platform formerly known as the Textual Communities Production version. The primary site is https://textualcommunities.com; the address https://textualcommunities.org now redirects to this site. Class structure 39 Lessons were structured in three-hour blocks, with a short break. The first part of each lesson iswas dedicated to the history of a particular script, its characteristic features, and the changes in writing technologies during that period. The course beginsbegan with Old English manuscripts but includesalso included Latin, Old French, Old and Middle English texts. To accommodate every one of the scriptseach script, we discussdiscussed the evolution and use of specific characters in different periodseach period, as well as contemporary abbreviations and their meanings. Generally, theeach lecture concludesconcluded by showing particularities present in thesample pages towhich students would then transcribe as well as, including ambiguous signs, as well as and extra-textual features (damage to the manuscript, scribal corrections, etc.) that might cause difficulty. 40 The rest of the class was dedicated to practical transcription, during which time each student worked on their individual transcriptions. The setup of Textual Communities focuses on understanding the text as an instance of a work preserved in individual folia within a manuscript (Work/Manuscript/Folio; see Figure 1), but this is not practical when one expects students to work mostly independently of each other. 41 Figure 1: Textual Communities screen capture showing the ontological structure “work/manuscript/folio.” 42 In production environments, the point of collaboration within textual communitiesTextual Communities is that different participants work on different manuscript passages or, if they work on the same, that they work on different parts of the workflow (e.g., transcribing, checking, etc.)..; see figure 2). It is also assumed, in most cases, that contributors will use their own technology (i.e., computers, operating systems, etc.), albeit with minimal technological requirements. In a classroom environment, however, neither of these assumptions is true. In the first place, accommodation and equity concerns mean that the system must be adapted so that students can both use their own technology or make use of university-provided equipment. In the secondFirst, the students are all learning the same skills from the same manuscripts, meaning that the community works in parallel rather than serial in a production environment. Second, accommodation and equity concerns necessitate that the system be adapted to allow students to use their own technology or utilize university-provided equipment. 43 Figure 2: Illustration of the different workflows for production (where multiple people work on different parts of a document) and classroom (where each student transcribes and is evaluated on the same parts of the same document) 44 Our classes were scheduled in a lab equipped with Apple computers to ensure that students had access to sufficient computer power, regardless of their personal means. But in many cases — (indeed most —) students preferred to work on their laptops or tablets (— in some cases, using special adaptations required for various accommodations).. Before the beginning of the semester, we registered individual students with Textual Communities and added them to a community called “Paleography 2023Paleography2023.” This allowed us to upload manuscript images from various sources and place them in separate folders, each corresponding to a particular student. The images were selected to correspond with the topics and chronology being followed in class (a list of the texts used for our lessons can be found in Bordalejo, 2024). 45 For the course, we set up a community called “Paleography2023.” Instead of separating the pages according to manuscripts as would have been done in a production environment, we created individual folders for each student and populated them with images of the different manuscript pages assigned to the class (see Figure 2 and Figure 3Figures 3 and 4, and cf. Figures 1 and 2). 46 Figure 23: Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified structure, “course/person.” 47 During the practical portion of the class, we walked around the classroom, making sureensuring that the students could make sense of the text and answer questions. Frequently, questions leadled to conversations about interpretation and misinterpretation, opinions, and more advanced discussions about the implications of different transcription choices. Students often shared their perspectives on the text and its interpretation collaboratively. Each student was working on the assigned pages for the day, but was encouraged to work at their own pace. Although, as an instructor, one might prefer to keep students working at a similar pace, one of the significant advantages of working within Textual Communities is that students can take ownership of their time and choose when and how to work. This is particularly noticeable towards the end of the semester, as students have gained confidence and are less hesitant to make their own decisions. 48 Figure 34: Textual Communities screen capture showing the modified structure, “course/person/folio.” 49 If particular manuscripts turned out to be challenging, the class swapped completed transcriptions for peer correction as the class as a whole read the text together. A few students wanted to pair up outside of class for peer correction, and although they could have done. If this just by swapping log-in credentials, they were already familiar enough withwas requested, the system to realize that by being assigned toprofessor or teaching assistants could assign their peers’ transcriptions to them for review within Textual Communities, there would be a. A record of the changes made to the student’s original transcription would be visible, as Textual Communities has a version control system that allows users to revert to previous versions so that changes made are visible. Checking student work 50 Although it might appear that a system allowing the transcription of primary sources would present a systembe intrinsically geared to paleography teachingclass, there are no mechanisms within Textual Communities to evaluate the accuracy of the transcription of individual characters. This required that checking and evaluation be done independently of the system by the instructor(s) and teaching assistant(s). 51 From an instructor’s perspective, the biggest drawback of Textual Communities is that it does not have a feature to correct the submitted transcriptions automatically. Although we do not discarddismiss the ideadesirability for pedagogical purposes of the implementation ofimplementing a correction module within Textual Communitiesthe system, this is not a requirement for classroom use, as correcting individual transcriptions is not a particularly onerous task. In the endUltimately, we usedemployed three methods of correction: instructor- correction, peer- correction, and self-correction. After all students had submitted a particular transcriptiontheir transcriptions, the instructor read the manuscriptmanuscripts aloud. This allowsenabled students to self-assess, correct their work, and discuss differentexplore various transcription options. We also tried transcription exchange, during which students gave each other access to transcriptions to evaluate each other’s accuracy. 52 During the semester, as students became more proficient, they were encouraged to revise their transcriptions to make themensure they were as accurate as possible. At the same time, they were given different choices: to retain all abbreviations, to expand them, or to use encoding to reflect both states. We discussed the advantages and disadvantages of each approach and why they might want to selectchoose one rather thanover the other. These techniques not only maintain students’ engagement but also offer an opportunity to test acquired skills in self-guided work. We recognizeacknowledge that we follow in the footsteps of the proponents of Critical Digital Pedagogy (, as will be discussed below).. So we aim to emphasize students' roleroles in their educational journey. In this light, we work towardsstrive to foster students’ independent thinking and self-determined work. 53 Although the initial aim of implementing Textual Communities was to ensure that the class could easily continue online if required, we soon realized its enormous potential to exercise student self-regulation, independence, and confidence-building. The practical format of the class, togethercombined with supervised independent work, was well received asbecause it differed from most classes in our department, most of which centertypically focus on analysis and close reading. Teaching assistant’s perspective 54 To support the instructor in the process of providing constructive feedback and help students improve their skills, the role of the teaching assistant (TA)s’ role in this novel class set-up is of great importance. First of all, TAs have to be aware of the course'scourse design and ideally contribute to it by working alongside the instructor. This collaboration can yield many benefits not only to their overall professional development as prospective educators but also to enhance course delivery. Being liminal figures between students and instructors, they can leverage a privileged observation point, which enables TAs to provide insights from both perspectives –— the instructor’s and the students’.students.’ TAs must actively participate in class activities, almost as if they were enrolled students, to assess progress and identify issues effectively. This involves transcribing texts before the start of each class, which allows the TAs to understand the challenges posed by each transcription. Since each scribe’s work is unique, being familiar with potential problems in a text enhances their ability to respond quickly and effectively. This proactive approach ensures that TAs are well-prepared to support students and address any difficulties during the course. While the TAs’ presence enriches the learning experience for both students and the TAs themselves, it is essential to avoid the drawback of students becoming overly dependent on them. 55 Another of the domains where TAs can prove very beneficial to the course is the evaluation of the difficulty of each task as well as the weekly workload. As the course progresses, the TA importance does not diminish but instead changes according to different factors. When the students begin the course, their unfamiliarity with both the tools (XML-TEI encoding and the peculiarities of the Textual Communities Sandbox, above all) and the scripts (insular minuscule, caroline, gothic, etc.) makes the TAs fundamental to letin providing the students receive moreearly personalized and timely feedback, which that is essential for the development of these skills. The students may also struggle with the discontinuities that characterize each period. For instance, once the students are well acquainted with the variations of the gothica textualis hand they will then have to readjust themselves to the knowledge of a fairly distinct hand such as the anglicana. This struggle, together with the fatigue of the semester, usually referred to as “exhaustion” or “burnout” in the literature (Galbraith and Merrill, 2012; Law, 20162007), often requires diversified types of additional support to students, especially considering their different learning styles and eventual needs. 56 This means that generally, TAs serve as mentors for students. Having been involved in transcription projects and having first-hand experience of the issues the students may encounter, they provide hands-on guidance, troubleshoot technical problems, and encourage students to explore the tools autonomously. This last part is fundamental since the pedagogical significance of a TArole should always be that of offering ongoing support while avoiding the risk of creating a situation for which the students solely depend on the TA. In line with the self-centred learning strategy adopted by the course, TAs should focusfocused on empowering students to develop their problem-solving skills and independence rather than providing solutions too readily. This balance ensuresensured that students benefitbenefited from the support of TAs without compromising their learning and growth, considering that student’sstudents’ learning autonomy should always be at the core of their activities, helping students develop self-confidence and the necessary skills to navigate the challenges of digital transcriptions autonomously. This relates to fundamental metacognitive skills –— the awareness of one’s own learning processes–: TAs must let students develop these skills in their own ways. For example, they are bridging the gap between theoretical knowledge of a handwriting’s characteristics and the practical application of that knowledge to understand the idiosyncrasies of a given manuscript via the student’s own transcription decisions. 57 Another challenge is managing the feedback. Correcting transcriptions –even in small classes– is a labour-intensive activity and reflects the shortcomings of Textual Communities, which has not been conceived to meet the demands of a classroom. To address this issue, an interface of automated grading tools to assess transcriptions and give immediate feedback would have to be integrated into the platform. This would greatly alleviate the workload of the instructors and the TAs, tracking students' progress and streamlining the submission of assignments, which is currently carried out with hand-and-eye methods. Every transcription has to be checked and then recorded on a spreadsheet by hand according to a formula counting the transcriptions for each of the 12 modules. These values are then converted to a percentage and a corresponding letter grade, weighted into the final average according to the syllabus. If, instead, this workload could be lightened by implementing this process into Textual Communities and perhaps making it interoperable with the API system of the academic Moodle. StudentStudent’s Perspective 58 In both instances of the course offered (in Spring 2023 and 2024), the introductory class was centred around explaining what transcription is and theits different types of transcription.(diplomatic, etc.). Textual Communities was not introduced to students immediately. Instead, they were presented with an image of a page of “Alice’s Adventures Under Ground” handwritten byin Wonderland” in Lewis CarrollCarroll’s handwriting, with the text meandering and curving across the page. They were asked to transcribe the page onto a paper by hand. This was an initial challenge to see what students perceived as being essential aspects of transcribing. Would they keep the shape of the words on the page? Would they copy the page numbers on the original image's corners? Would they include the virgules and dashes used? This practice allowedenabled students to understand how transcribing is an act of interpretation carried out with regard to a larger purpose and how many differentmultiple transcriptions couldcan exist for onea single text. Indeed we use this method in teaching other computational skills to students at the University of Lethbridge: by beginning with an illustration of the problem a system (such as TEI markup) is is intended to address (such as recording an interpretation of a document) and then asking students to come with their own approach before teaching them about existing methods. We believe that this allows students to understand the canonical systems better by illustrating the problem they were developed to address. 59 With thisthe problem in mind, students were then introduced to the Textual Communities platform. While the instructor and TAs initially guided the students on how to use the website's basic features — how to access their assigned pages, save their work, etc. — the students were left to decide how their transcriptions would look. They had to decide what they wanted to include in their work. If, forFor example, if a line was crossed out and something new text was written above the deleted text, they had to decide if they wantedwhether to include both parts, one or the other, or indicate the deleted text, etc. Student transcriptions would often differdiffered significantly from one another in significant ways due to thesethe decisions that had to be made throughout their work. The instructor and TAs emphasized that making different choices about what to include or not include was not necessarily right or wrong; it was just a matter of interpretation. Perhaps the best statement about the student perspective in our course comes from one of our students herself, Victoria Simmons, quoted here with permission: 60 As the Rural Diary Archive [a project the student was looking at] suggests, crowdsourcing of transcription can be accomplished not only on a global or national scale but also on a smaller, local scale by using a classroom setting. A similar type of collaborative experience was created in our classroom when we focused on discussing certain parts of manuscripts that were comparatively complex to transcribe. When there was a particular section of our assigned manuscript that was more difficult –— due to multiple adjacent characters written in minimum for example –— the class would be encouraged to individually express to the class how they had interpreted the characters when they were transcribing. In most circumstances, this resulted in many unique interpretations expressed by classmates as to how they visually followed the connection of ligatures into what they believed may have been the scribe’s intended characters. By listening to multiple people voice their reasoning behind transcribing the writing in the way that they had chosen, the entire class was invited to look at a variety of possible interpretations for each transcription. The most important result of this experience is that each individual is challenged to question their own method of transcription. This technique is beneficial to the field of paleography because it prevents transcribers from settling on a single, definitive – and potentially incorrect or incomplete — perspective of the transcription. The benefit of this experience is amplified when it comes to global crowdsourcing projects, such as those mentioned above, which allow both beginners and experts to provide a greater variety of original viewpoint. (Simmons, student paper, 2023) 61 As Simmons notes, “many unique interpretations [were] expressed by classmates … By listening to multiple people voice their reasoning behind transcribing the writing in the way that they had chosen, the entire class was invited to look at various possible interpretations for each transcription. The most important result of this experience is that each individual is challenged to question their own method of transcription” (Simmons, student paper, 2023). Viewing other students’ pages and their work on Textual Communities also allowed those who were not present in class to have still be a part of this experience of seeing other people’s interpretations of the text. 62 Students were also encouraged to work together on transcriptions and to frequently ask questions as the instructor and TAs were in the room for the working period. As described by one studentSimmons, a “collaborative experience was created in our classroom” (Simmons, student paper, 2023). This, combined with the previously established attitude of transcription as interpretation, established that the classwork was not focused on being “right” or “wrong.” Instead, the priority was to learn important characteristics and traits of the various hands taught and try their best to complete the assigned pages given. Some students initially seemed apprehensive about the lack of a “grade” they would receive for their transcriptions. As a result, many of the early transcriptions took students a long time to complete. To easealleviate this worryconcern, the beginning of later classes was devoted to looking atidentifying common errors among multiple students. In both course iterations (Spring 2023 and Spring 2024), the instructor and TAs adjusted the amount of correcting done to transcriptions depending on how much the students requested feedback for their work. Textual Communities allows those categorized asenables instructors categorized on the platform to access student pages and edit or add comments to their transcriptions so that, allowing students can accessto view comments about their work outside of class time. 63 Accessing Textual Communities outside of class time from any computer is one of the significant benefits of the platform, allowing students to work outside of the set class-time working periods. They could sign in to their Textual Communities account from any computer. This, combined with the rule in the course that the pages only had to be done by the end of the semester, allowed students the flexibility and freedom to complete coursework at their own pace. This student-centred approach was enabled by the flexibility offered by the Textual Communities platform. 64 The collaborative and accessible platform of Textual Communities allowed students to work together with classmates and consider the many possible interpretations that transcription might involve. It also allowed students to access their work and view corrections or comments made about it on their own time, which might contribute to easing students’ worries about periods in the semester that required more of their attention — they could work on their pages at any point, as long as all of them were completed by the end of the semester. In short, using Textual Communities as a platform encouraged students to collaborate, consider the interpretative process of transcriptions, not focus too hard on mistakes they might have considered themselves to have made, and gave them the freedom to work on assigned pages at times that worked best for their personalized schedules. Discussion 65 The core innovation in using Textual Communities for teaching is that students make their own research decisions about what to transcribe and why, with instructors supporting them in implementing these decisions. As O’Donnell et al. (2016b) argue, the traditional division between “research” — i.e., what the professor engages in and is protected by academic freedom — and “teaching” — i.e., when students are told what to do and how to do it — misrepresents the nature of Humanities scholarship and limits student learning by preventing meaningful engagement in research in a meaningful way. This practice also reflects what we call the “First Law of Humanities Computing,” which refers to the fact that any application of computation to a humanities problem seems to require a fundamental examination of the purposes behind the original activity (O’Donnell 2016a). Asking students to consider why they want to transcribe these manuscripts, what they hope to achieve by doing so, and how they can match their methods to their goals, is a way of asking them to engage in critical reflection on their own learning — both within the course itself and, of course, more broadly within their programs. Unlike non-digital work, where intuition and analogy often can serve as guides, digital work demands conscious design and algorithmic thinking. By allowing students to exercise judgment and pursue their own questions, Textual Communities collapses this gap. It invites students to engage in the same intellectual freedoms that define research itself. 66 As we described earlier, this meant that there were numerous active discussions on the implications of specific choices during the transcription process. While the lecturing and grading resembled more traditional class structure and dynamics, which relates to the intrinsic nature of any paleography class, the use of Textual Communities provided students with tools and methods — high-resolution, digital facsimiles, peer dialogue, collaboration, and meaningful input into the methods they used to transcribe (scribal corrections, unclear textual segments, a change in scribal “hands,” and letter forms) — that allowed them to set their own research questions, exercise their viewpoints and interpretations, and pursue them according to their own critical judgments. 67 The version control system helps students to track their own variants of the text and can reconstruct their train of thought regarding their transcription work (for instance, where the student might interpret a mark modification from a scribe or ignore it). In contrast to traditional approaches to paleography, Textual Communities prompts students to reflect on their actions as they are taking place in an even more profound manner. The reason for this is that it compels the students to face the logic of the machine and its one-sidedness, which forces fixed choices where human interpretation would allow ambiguity, requiring students to decide definitively between possibilities that a manuscript might leave open. For instance, the XML-TEI markup language allows for hundreds of ways to encode features within a single page, with variations such as different forms of damage to the page (such as water damage, erasure, fire, animal, scraping, etc.). This level of critical engagement with the problem — the problem-solving itself — creates a beneficial dialogue, which involves all the members, from the experts (teachers and TAs) to the students' peers. Some of the students within the classroom already have an intuitive understanding of what is going on, and they have an opportunity to share this with the class. This peer collaboration throughout the course allows students to see how others are interpreting and solving the problems they see on the pages. For instance, students were asked to attempt to recognize the material of the page on which the text appeared (whether parchment or paper). As a result, interpretative uncertainty in the document can be rendered into different solutions. One student might interpret a letter form completely differently from another — for example, reading pride instead of þrid (a variant spelling of “third”) based on the common confusion between thorn and p — or assume a sense of intentionality from the scribe regarding what another might view as an error. 68 In the foreword of the collection Critical Digital PedagogyCritical Digital Pedagogy edited by Stommel, Friend, and MorrisStommel, Friend, and Morris during the pandemic (Stommel et al., 2020a)(Stommel et al., 2020a), Benjamin argues that thissuch experience has also workedfunctions as “a portal, a gateway between one world and the next” (Benjamin, 2020)2020) leading to a greater integration of digital tools not initially developed for teaching purposes in education — as in the case of Textual Communities. In the introduction to the same collection, the authors also state that “[n]othing in edtech was built for humans. Thus far, our edtech machines were taught only to speak to other machines” (Stommel et al., 2020b).Stommel et al., 2020b). An example of this is represented by video conferencing tools like Zoom that “were not built to meet the moral challenge of a present moment like this one” (Stommel et al., 2020b).(Stommel et al., 2020b). They have allowed, however, for synchronous collaborative learning experiences and virtual classroom discussions without replacing the classroom, which is and remains “unique” and distinct from “the architecture of the Web” (Stommel et al., 2020b.).(Stommel et al., 2020b). 69 This concept of the uniqueness of the classroom, “with all its limitations” (hooks, 1994, p. 207)(hooks, 1994, p. 207), makes it “a location of possibility,” that allows for both the empowerment of social actors and the disruption of traditional forms of teaching. In hooks’ view, education should be a space for freedom and ultimately a transformative process. She advocates for engaged pedagogy, which understands classrooms as a site for self-guided exploration and mutual participation. While she extends this approach beyond a traditional academic setting, our practice of using Textual Communities has been an attempt to integrate these suggestions meaningfully. 70 This relates to the sort of We have kept hooks’ perspective in mind in constructing this environment that we have striven to construct for theour paleography class. In this sense, oneOne of theour main objectives was to try and “responsibilize” students in the way defined dy (Spencer, 2018, p. 291)by Spencer (2018, p. 291). For Spencer, renegotiating the “social contract” between professor and student within the classroom is one of them. Spencer introduces this concept at the outset of the article, highlighting the limited roles each party can ethically operate (Spencer 2018,(Spencer, 2018, p. 287). According to this contract, the relationship between the professor, responsible for the course content and grading criteria, and the student, seeking to acquire skills to advance their future career prospects, resembles in its fundamental features a customer-provider neoliberal transaction. For Spencer, precisely this transactional dynamic is utterly problematic since it creates a power imbalance, where the professor supervises, and the student works at the pace dictated by the employer, potentially for the professor'sprofessor’s benefit (Spencer, 2018, pp. 287–288). 71 Moreover, this power imbalance makes it difficult for students to raise objections, and thus a need to acknowledge and constructively engage with this issue for the benefit of both students and professors (Spencer, 2018, pp. 288–289). Fellmayer (Fellmayer, 2020)Fellmayer (2020) stresses the significance of reflexivity in coping with this asymmetry by acknowledging one's privilege and agency in benefiting from an inequitable society, which impedes meaningful disruption. Therefore, our focal point was to create a transformative educational experience for their students through digital tools in the framework established in the field of critical digital pedagogy during the pandemic. 72 Critical digital pedagogy is characterized by a deep engagement with the use of tools and technologies. Still, it is configured as a practice that centres on questioning and reflecting on these tools and their usage (Stommel et al., 2020b)., while encouraging students to question and reflect on those same tools and methods (Stommel et al., 2020b). This approach represents an expansion of the work of Paulo Freire, a Brazilian educator who criticized educational institutions for their tendency to silence or marginalize dissenting voices in his seminal work "Pedagogy of the Oppressed" (Freire, 2000)(Freire, 2000) and was exiled for his views, being deeply committed to rethinking education and advocating for more inclusive and equitable learning environments. 73 Critical digital pedagogy seeks to dismantle impediments to learning. It argues that it is especially fruitful to probe the ground and identify the gap between theory and practice, but of course, it does not suggest that there are easy answers to the challenges of remote learning. While it can be helpful, it must be employed thoughtfully to be effective. Stommel, Friend, and Morris state that:Stommel, Friend, and Morris state that: 74 The word “pedagogy,” as we use it, defines the work of education at the intersection of theory and practice — the act of teaching that derives from reflection and which inspires reflection again. Pedagogy is both where “critical” and “digital” terminate, and also the whole terrain of teaching. (Stommel et al., 2020b)(Stommel et al., 2020b) 75 The triad “critical,” “digital,” and “pedagogical” must be kept without privileging “digital” at the expense of “critical” or of “pedagogy.” Suppose one only emphasizes the critical aspect of teaching. In that case, there is a risk of reducing it to a mere instrument, relegating the task of reflecting on teaching to the humanities and separating critical thinking from STEM fields, for instance. This narrow approach not only limits the potential impact of critical work, but also underestimates the vast array of teaching and learning activities that require criticality and a commitment to dismantling institutional or societal obstacles to learning (Stommel et al., 2020b)(Stommel et al., 2020b). However, the ideal process of dismantling barriers to learning has been further complicated by the challenges that have arisen during the pandemic period, which have added new layers of complexity to a pre-existing multifaceted landscape to let students take ownership of their learning and promote freedom in the classroom. 76 Effecting this is not necessarily easy, as Maha Bali argues in the same collection ((Bali, 2020)2020), suggesting it is too easy to focus on theory and not enough on praxis. As she claims of her teaching context at the American University of Cairo: “[c]ritical pedagogy [...] is not about knowing how to do everything right or getting it right the first time, or every time. It is about putting faith in our learners to take control of their learning and teach us, each other, and themselves in the process” (Bali, 2020).(Bali, 2020). Essentially, this learning approach is based on the fact that she does not “make everything explicit on the first day,” stating the importance of “of learning from each other” and having “flexible and negotiable” syllabi, as well as “the importance of dialogue and talk about respectful disagreement and the importance of class participation” to continuing to “explore the dungeon” in an autonomous manner (Bali, 2020; emphasis in the original). 77 (Bali, 2020; emphasis in the original). Moving by these premises, we think that digital technologies are an ideal means to promote student autonomy, as they provide a toolkit for students to navigate the learning process independently. This idea is further echoed by Cathy N. Davidson’s suggestion to structure a "“student-centered class"” that utilizes technology to the extent desired by the instructor, which allows the instructor to maintain control while also empowering students to take an active role in service of their pedagogical needs at the same time fostering a dynamic and rewarding learning environment that is flexible and effective (Davidson, 2020). 78 Pete Rorabaugh (Rorabaugh, 2020Pete Rorabaugh (2020) draws from the idea that teaching is a moral act with significant implications for educators, including the ethical dimension, to argue that a critical approach to pedagogy is consistent with the goals of a digitally-infused curriculum because digital culture offers new opportunities to achieve that goal. Rorabaugh argues that digital tools have the potential to empower students in the digital sphere by providing them with new opportunities for human connectivity and enabling them to refocus on how power works in the classroom: 79 Digital tools offer the opportunity to refocus how power works in the classroom. In its evolution from passive consumption to critical production — from the cult of the expert to a culture of collaboration — the critical and digital classroom emerges as a site of intellectual and moral agency. ((Rorabaugh, 2020) 80 In Rorabaugh’s view, critical digital pedagogies aim to disrupt the conventional hierarchical structure of the classroom, allowing students to take charge of their learning and play an active role in their education. There is a moral obligation to engage learners in a democratic discovery of their own empowerment. By utilizing digital tools, students are given the opportunity to interact and collaborate with co-learners across various platforms on the internet. However, this kind of learning environment requires a critical pedagogue who is knowledgeable and skilled in selecting appropriate tools and activities and can blend them with an interactive learning community. 81 For us, the pandemic served as a catalyst for exploring new approaches to teaching and learning that prioritize critical thinking, student-centerednesscentredness, and the thoughtful use of digital tools. Through the practical application of these principles, we have been able to create a new kind of classroom environment that is responsive to the post-pandemic needs and realities of our students, and that fosters engagement, collaboration, and meaningful learning experiences. As we continue to navigate the ongoing challenges presented by the pandemic and beyond, these principles will continue to guide our work as educators and serve as a foundation for innovative and effective pedagogical practices. Conclusions Conclusion 82 The implementation of Textual Communities as an environment to teach paleography proved to be advantageous from various perspectives. It is true that, if we were inever to face a situation similar to that of March 2020 again, we would be able to move into online teaching almost effortlessly. However, using an online environment as a teaching resource has other advantages. Mainly, this environment enables students to find their own work rhythm. 83 Because paleography is a skill that improves with practice, it is not uncommon for beginners to have a great deal ofexperience significant difficulty and advance at what might seem a glacialslow pace. As students practice, they are likely to work fastermore efficiently and more accurately. By using Textual Communities, our students are able tocan manage their time in a way that is more suitable tosuits their personal circumstances. For example, someone might start a transcription during the allocated class period but not be able to finish it. At home, they can access the system and work at convenient times. Each with each change gets recorded in the versioning component. 84 As the students became familiar with Textual Communities, they were able to make arrangements for collaboration with others and create a system of peer evaluation and support to help each other become more accurate and achieve better results. Fostering this cooperative spirit resulted inled to the growth of the parties involved, not justonly in the study of paleography but also in their development as researchers and human beingsindividuals. 85 It is certainly the case that the pandemic induced an acceleration in the usage of digital technologies in teaching and learning. While their initial adoption during the pandemic may have been driven by necessity, the tools’ effectiveness in enhancing the learning experience can still be effective in the post-pandemic period, as we have demonstrated in our paper. The potential for innovation and renovation implicit in many arguments regarding the digital turn during the pandemic permeates initiatives such as ours. In seeing the pandemic experience as an opportunity to pushencourage educators into creative use of to creatively utilize available resources, we turnedtransformed the challenge into an occasion for reorganizing the classroom space asinto a hybrid environment. 86 The uncertainties inof a post-pandemic world have forcedcompelled us to be more imaginative and resourceful, pushingprompting us in ways we might not have considered before. We have been reminded that we can adapt successfully and find new ways to engage our students with our subject while giving them a sense of independence and freedom. Acknowledgments 87 The authors thank Victoria Simmons for contributing a reflection on classroom-based transcription practices, which has been included in this article, which helped shape our understanding of the students’ perspective. We also thank the referees and editors at DHQ for their thoughtful comments and recommendations on an earlier draft of this article. 88 References 89 Akbar, M. (2016) ‘Digital technology shaping teaching practices in higher education’, Frontiers in ICT 3, 3(February). doi: Akbar, M. (2016) ‘Digital technology shaping teaching practices in higher education’, Frontiers in ICT 3(1). https://doi.org/10.3389/fict.2016.00001. 90 Badilla Q., Graciela, M., Careaga-Butter, M., and Fuentes-Henríquez, C. (2021) ‘Critical and prospective analysis of online education in pandemic and post-pandemic contexts’, Aloma: Revista de Psicologia, Ciències de l’Educació i de l’Esport, 38(2), pp. 23–32. doi: https://doi.org/10.51698/aloma.2020.38.2.23-32. 91 Bali, M. (2020) ‘Critical pedagogy: Intentions and realities’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.) Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. . 92 Bali, M. (2020) ‘Critical pedagogy: Intentions and realities’, in Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.) Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/critical-pedagogy-intentions-and-realities/ (Accessed: 16 October 2024). 93 Barrett-Fox, R., Bayne, B., Cooper, V., and Espinosa, G. (2020) ‘How the Coronavirus pandemic will change our future teaching’, Religion and American Culture, 30(2), pp.147–86. doi:Barrett-Fox, R., et al. (2020) ‘How the Coronavirus pandemic will change our future teaching’, Religion and American Culture, 30(2), pp.147–86. https://doi.org/10.1017/rac.2020.10. 94 Benjamin, R. (2020) ‘Foreword’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Benjamin, R. (2020) ‘Foreword’, in Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/foreword/ (Accessed 16 October 2024). 95 Bordalejo, B.. . (2024.) ENG 3850/ HIST 3850 Paleography 2023. Zenodo. doi: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13941931. 96 Davidson, C. N. (2020) ‘Why start with pedagogy? 4 good reasons, 4 good solutions’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Bordalejo, B., and Robinson, P. (2016) ‘Textual communities’, in Digital Humanities 2016, pp. 876-77. Available at: https://lirias.kuleuven.be/retrieve/534266. (Accessed 25 April 2025). 97 Careaga-Butter, M., Badilla Quintana, M. G., and Fuentes-Henríquez, C. (2020) ‘Critical and prospective analysis of online education in pandemic and post-pandemic contexts’, Aloma: Revista de Psicologia, Ciències de l’Educació i de l’Esport, 38(2), pp. 23–32. https://doi.org/10.51698/aloma.2020.38.2.23-32. 98 Davidson, C. N. (2020) ‘Why start with pedagogy? 4 good reasons, 4 good solutions’, in Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/why-start-with-pedagogy-4-good-reasons-4-good-solutions/. (Accessed: 16 October 2024). 99 Edgar, A., and Sedgwick, P.R. (eds.). (1999) Key concepts in cultural theory. Key Concepts Series. London; New York: Routledge. 100 Fellmayer, J. (2020) ‘Disruptive pedagogy and the practice of freedom’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Edgar, A., and Sedgwick, P.R. (eds.) (1999) Key concepts in cultural theory. Key Concepts Series. London; New York: Routledge. 101 Fellmayer, J. (2020) ‘Disruptive pedagogy and the practice of freedom’, in Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/disruptive-pedagogy-and-the-practice-of-freedom/. (Accessed: 16 October 2024). 102 Forti, L. (2023) Corpus use in italian language pedagogy: Exploring the effects of data-driven learning. 1st edn. Routledge Applied Corpus Linguistics. Abingdon, Oxon; New York, NY: Routledge.Forti, L. (2023) Corpus use in Italian language pedagogy: Exploring the effects of data-driven learning. 1st edn. Routledge Applied Corpus Linguistics. Abingdon, Oxon; New York, NY: Routledge. 103 Galbraith, C. S., and Merrill, G. B. (2012) ‘Academic and work-related burnout: A longitudinal study of working undergraduate university business students’, Journal of College Student Development, 53(3), pp. 453–63. doi: https://doi.org/10.1353/csd.2012.0044453–63. https://doi.org/10.1353/csd.2012.0044. 104 Freire, P. (2000) Pedagogy of the oppressed. 30th anniversary edn. New York: Continuum. 105 Gleason, B., and Manca, S. (2020) ‘Curriculum and instruction: Pedagogical approaches to teaching and learning with Twitter in higher education’, On the Horizon, 28(1), pp.1–8. 106 Hofer, S. I., Nistor, N., and Scheibenzuber, C. (2021) ‘Online teaching and learning in higher education: Lessons learned in crisis situations’, Computers in Human Behavior, 121 (August),106789. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106789. 107 hooks, b. 1994 Teaching to transgress: Education as the practice of freedom. New York: Routledge. 108 Kim, D. (2018) Disrupting the digital humanities. 1st edn. Santa Barbara, CA: Punctum Books. 109 Lai, K.-W. (2011) ‘Digital technology and the culture of teaching and learning in higher education’, Australasian Journal of Educational Technology 27(8). doi:Freire, P. (2000) Pedagogy of the oppressed. 30th anniversary edn. New York: Continuum. 110 Gleason, B., and Manca, S. (2020) ‘Curriculum and instruction: Pedagogical approaches to teaching and learning with Twitter in higher education’, On the Horizon, 28(1), pp.1–8. https://doi.org/10.1108/OTH-03-2019-0014. 111 Hofer, S. I., Nistor, N., and Scheibenzuber, C. (2021) ‘Online teaching and learning in higher education: Lessons learned in crisis situations’, Computers in Human Behavior, 121,106789. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106789. 112 hooks, b. (1994) Teaching to transgress: Education as the practice of freedom. New York: Routledge. 113 Kim, D. (2018) Disrupting the digital humanities. 1st edn. Santa Barbara, CA: Punctum Books. 114 Lai, K.-W. (2011) ‘Digital technology and the culture of teaching and learning in higher education’, Australasian Journal of Educational Technology 27(8). https://doi.org/10.14742/ajet.892. 115 Law, D. W. (2007) ‘Exhaustion in university students and the effect of coursework involvement’, Journal of American College Health, 55(4), pp. 239–245.. doi: https://doi.org/10.3200/JACH.55.4.239-245https://doi.org/10.3200/JACH.55.4.239-245. 116 Lohr, A., Stadler, M., Schultz-Pernice, F., Chernikova, O., Sailer, M., Fischer, F., and Sailer, M. (2021) ‘On powerpointers, clickerers, and digital pros: Investigating the initiation of digital learning activities by teachers in higher education’, Computers in Human Behavior, 119 (June), 106715. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106715. 117 Mauss, M. (1966) The gift: Forms and functions of exchange in archaic societies. London: Cohen and West LTD. 118 Murphy, M. P. A. (2020) ‘COVID-19 and emergency eLearning: Consequences of the securitization of higher education for post-pandemic pedagogy’ Contemporary Security Policy, 41(3), pp. 492–505. doi:Lohr, A., et al. (2021) ‘On powerpointers, clickerers, and digital pros: Investigating the initiation of digital learning activities by teachers in higher education’, Computers in Human Behavior, 119, 106715. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2021.106715. 119 Mauss, M. (1966) The gift: Forms and functions of exchange in archaic societies. London: Cohen and West LTD. 120 Murphy, M. P. A. (2020) ‘COVID-19 and emergency eLearning: Consequences of the securitization of higher education for post-pandemic pedagogy’, Contemporary Security Policy, 41(3), pp. 492–505. https://doi.org/10.1080/13523260.2020.1761749. 121 Rinaldo, S. B., Tapp, S., and Laverie, A.D. (2011) ‘Learning by tweeting: Using Twitter as a pedagogical tool’, Journal of Marketing Education, 33(2), pp. 193–203. 122 Rorabaugh, P. (2020) ‘Occupy the digital: Critical pedagogy and new media’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. O’Donnell, D. P. (2016a) ‘A first law of humanities computing.’ Journal of Brief Ideas. Available at: http://beta.briefideas.org/ideas/2887a2c8127dea5e64e512ae7f6a2407. (Accessed 25 April 2025). 123 O’Donnell, D. P., et al. (2016b). ‘The third academic freedom’, Light on Teaching, pp. 4–9. http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3596098. (Accessed 25 April 2025). 124 Rinaldo, S. B., Tapp, S., and Laverie, A.D. (2011) ‘Learning by tweeting: Using Twitter as a pedagogical tool’, Journal of Marketing Education, 33(2), pp. 193–203. https://doi-org.uleth.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/0273475311410852. 125 Rorabaugh, P. (2020) ‘Occupy the digital: Critical pedagogy and new media’, in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/chapter/occupy-the-digital-critical-pedagogy-and-new-media/. (Accessed: 16 October 2024). 126 Spencer, D. C. K. (2018) ‘Disrupting labor in digital humanities; Or, the classroom is not your crowd’, in D. Kim (ed.), Disrupting the digital humanities. 1st edn. Santa Barbara, CA: Punctum Books, pp. 273–94. 127 Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, M. S. (2020a) Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc.Robinson, P., Nelson, B., and Klaassen, F. (2012) ‘The textual communities project’. Available at: https://www.interedition.eu/wp-content/bestanden/2012/03/7_2.pdf. (Accessed 25 April 2025). 128 Robinson, P, and Solopova, E. (1993) ‘Guidelines for transcription of the manuscripts of the wife of bath’s prologue’, in: Blake, N.F., Robinson, P.M.W. (eds.), The Canterbury Tales Project Occasional Papers, Office for Humanities Communication Publications. Office for Humanities Communication, Oxford, pp. 19–52. https://doi.org/10.5281/ZENODO.11954055 129 Spencer, D. C. K. (2018) ‘Disrupting labor in digital humanities; Or, the classroom is not your crowd’, in D. Kim (ed.), Disrupting the digital humanities. 1st edn. Santa Barbara, CA: Punctum Books, pp. 273–94. 130 Stack Overflow. (2024) ‘Stackoverflow developer survey’. Available at: https://survey.stackoverflow.co/2024/technology. (Accessed 25 April 2025). 131 Stommel, J., Friend, C., and Morris, M. S. (eds.) (2020a) Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/. (Accessed 16 October 2024). 132 ———. (2020b) “Introduction.” in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. ———. (2020b) “Introduction”. in Stommel, J. Friend, C. and Morris, S. M. (eds.), Critical digital pedagogy: A collection. Hybrid Pedagogy Inc. Available at: https://pressbooks.pub/cdpcollection/front-matter/introduction/. (Accessed 16 October 2024). 133 Torsello, C. S., Ackerley, K., and Castello, E. (2008) Corpora for university language teachers. vol. 74. Bristol: Peter Lang Group AG. 134 Thomas, J. D. E., and Blackwood, M. (2010) ‘Computer literacy and non-IS majors’, Information Systems Education Journal 8(58). https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1146785. 135 Torsello, C. S., Ackerley, K., and Castello, E. (eds.) (2008) Corpora for university language teachers. 74. Bristol: Peter Lang Group AG. 136 Wilcken, U. (1932) ‘Das Leydener Klammersystem’. Archiv Für Papyrusforschung 10, pp. 211–12. Preview  |  XML |  Print Article This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License.